Albert M. Cook Papers
Albert M. Cook Papers
1862-1878
Cook, Albert M.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Union soldier (1843-1872). Served as a clerk in the 123rd New York Volunteers during the Civil War, participated in Gettysburg and Atlanta Campaigns. Worked as a surveyor following war. Diaries (1862-1865); family correspondence (1862-1878); and memorabilia, including military certificates, Cook's company's muster-out roll, photographs, and newspapers.
148899
Biographical History
Albert M. Cook (1843-1872) was an American Civil War soldier and surveyor. Born on January 30, 1843, he left his home in Greenwich, New York in 1862 and enlisted as a private in the 123rd Regiment, New York Volunteers. He served as company clerk, participated in the Battle of Gettysburg, and later marched south with his regiment, entering Atlanta on September 2, 1864. At the time of his discharge on June 8, 1865 he held the rank of Sergeant. In 1869 he moved west to Girard, Kansas where he worked as surveyor. He died on February 23, 1872.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Albert M. Cook Papers contain Civil War letters, diaries, memorabilia, and some later correspondence. Correspondence consists of letters to his father Courtland C. Cook, his brother Frederick A. Cook, and his sister. The letters concern camp life and recount experiences on the battlefield. Included in the correspondence of the 1870s are a few letters from other family members and letters between Cook's sister and a suitor. The Diaries offer a more specific account of daily life during the war. Of interest in both correspondence and diaries are Cook's accounts of the execution of deserters and the shelling and occupation of Atlanta. Items of Memorabilia include Cook's promotion and discharge certificates, his company's muster-out roll, photographs of Cook and his brother Frederic, and contemporary newspapers.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and diaries are arranged chronologically. Items of memorabilia are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Civil War (U.S.); Cook, Albert M.; Cook family.; United States. Army -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865, Sources.; United States. Army -- New York Volunteers, 123rd.; Atlanta Campaign, 1864.; Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863.; Soldiers -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Diaries.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Military -- To 1900 -- Sources.; Certificates.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Muster rolls.; Newspapers.; Photographs.; Soldiers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1970.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1862 (Box 1)
  - 1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1865 (Box 1)
  - 1869-1872 (Box 1)
  - 1876-1878 (Box 1)
- Diaries
  - Fragments, 1862, August 6-9 (Box 1)
  - Volume 1, 1862, Aug 6 - 1863, Jan 17 (Box 1)
  - Volume 2, 1863, Jan 18 - Jul 12 (Box 1)
  - Volume 3, 1863, Jul 13 - 1864, Feb 18 (Box 1)
  - Volume 4, 1864, Feb 20 - Jul 7 (Box 1)
  - Volume 5, 1864, Jul 7 - Dec 17 (Box 1)
  - [no title], 1865, Mar 4 - Apr 19 (Box 1)
  - [no title], 1865, Apr 22 - Jun 12 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Certificate of promotion, 10 Jan 1864 (Box 1)
  - Death certificate, Frederic A. Cook, 21 Mar 1865 (Box 1)
  - Discharge certificate, Albert M. Cook, 8 Jun 1865 (Box 1)
  - The Evening Bulletin, Providence, Rhode Island, 12 Apr 1865 (Box 1)
  - Girard Press, Girard, Kansas, 15 Jul 1871 (Box 1)
  - Muster-out roll, Jun 1865 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Albert M. Cook and Frederick A. Cook, undated; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Soldiers' Voting Bill, New York, 1864 (Box 1)
  - Washington Co. People's Journal, Greenwich, New York, 30 Mar 1865 (Box 1)